Over here we have the question, a venturi
tube
has a pressure difference of 15,000
pascals.
The entrance radius is 3 cm, while the
exit
radius is 1 cm. What are the entrance
velocity,
exit velocity, and flow rate if the fluid
is
gasoline, which has a density of 700 kg
per
m3? So, first of all we know that this is
a
fluid question, so we would start off by
writing
the Bernoulli's equation. Now after
we do this, we realize that our question
involves
a venturi tube, which basically means that
the
y value doesn't change. Since the y value
doesn't
change, we can cancel out the terms that
involve
y. So we can cancel out these two terms,
and
what we're left with is p1 plus 1 over 2
pv1
squared equals p2 plus 1 over 2 pv2
squared.
Now, the question also states that the
pressure
difference is 15,000, so p1 minus p2 is
15,000.
So we want to isolate p1 minus p2.
We move p2 to the other side, and we move
this
thing to this side. So, 1 over 2 rho v2
squared
minus 1 over 2 rho v1 squared.
This would be 15,000 equals, you can
factor
out of 1 over 2 rho, 1 over 2 rho v2
squared
minus v1 squared.
We know rho is 700, so 1 over 2 rho would
be
350. Dividing that by this, we get 300
over 7 equals v2 squared minus v1 squared.
Now, what we have to do from here is,
since
we don't know v1 or v2, but we do know the
entrance
radius and the exit radius, that means
that
we should use the continuity equation,
which
basically states that the rate is
constant.
The rate would be v1 times a1 equals v2
times
a2. So, we know a1 and a2 because we know
the
radius. a1 would be pi times 3 squared,
which
would be equal to 9 pi, equals v2 times a2
would
be pi times 1 squared, which would be just
pi
times pi. So, cancelling out the pis, we
get
9 times v1 equals v2.
Now, since we have two equations, we can
easily
solve for a variable.
We can plug in v2 equals 9 v1.
We can substitute that into here. So, 300
over
7 equals 2.
v2 would be equal to 9 v1 squared minus v1
squared.
300 over 7 equals 81 v1 squared minus v1
squared. 300 over 7 equals 80 v1 squared.
And, when we solve for v1, we would get v1
equals
0.73 metres per second.
Now that we have v1, everything else
clicks
into place. We know that 9 times v1 equals
v2,
so that means v2 equals 9 v1, which is
equal
to 9 times 0.73. And, we get v2 would be
to 6.59 metres
per second. Now, all that's left for us to
calculate
from the question is it asks for the flow
rate.
The flow rate can be calculated using any
one.
Let's just use v2. So, rate would be equal
to
v2 times a2, which is the area.
We know v2 is 6.59, and a2 would be equal
to
pi times radius squared. And, since radius
is
just 1, that would just be equal to pi.
So,
the rate would ultimately be 20.69 metres
cubed
per second.